<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<search>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Hello World</title>
    <link href="/2023/07/26/hello-world/"/>
    <url>/2023/07/26/hello-world/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to my blog! My name is Alexander Zhang and this is my very first post.</p><h1 id="What-happened-before-the-birth-of-this-website"><a href="#What-happened-before-the-birth-of-this-website" class="headerlink" title="What happened before the birth of this website"></a>What happened before the birth of this website</h1><p>I have been considering building my own blog since 2022, but my lack of related knowledge prevented me from taking actions. Today, July 26th, 2023, I am happy to announce an official end of my sophomore year, which could also be considered as end of my bachelor life considering I have almost gathered all the course credits needed for graduation. A more reasonable date should be 9th July, but not until today have I finished all the short-term required missions (a TOEFL test is to blame for the delay).</p><p>For a long period of time, I recorded my thoughts on <a href="https://www.zhihu.com/people/professor-x-73/pins">Zhihu</a> and local word files on my computer. However, I found it hard to manage and review my records and I really hope to share some of the ideas to other people. So, eventually, I made up my mind to build up this blog to record my thoughts.</p><h1 id="What-is-this-blog-mainly-about"><a href="#What-is-this-blog-mainly-about" class="headerlink" title="What is this blog mainly about"></a>What is this blog mainly about</h1><p>Generally speaking, it’s about thoughts and knowledge.<br>Thoughts refer to philosophical thinkings and ideas gained from daily experiences.<br>Knowledge is mainly about physics, which is my major.</p><h1 id="How-this-blog-is-going-to-work"><a href="#How-this-blog-is-going-to-work" class="headerlink" title="How this blog is going to work"></a>How this blog is going to work</h1><p>I plan to use both Chinese and English to write blogs. Chinese for thoughts and English for knowledge. This result from the fact that, as a native Chinese speaker, it would be easier for me to express my emotions and thoughts precisely using Chinese. And I usually learn knowledge through English in the university.</p><h1 id="Why-“DASEIN”"><a href="#Why-“DASEIN”" class="headerlink" title="Why “DASEIN”"></a>Why “DASEIN”</h1><p>For a long time, I have been a great fan of Existentialism and I decided to use the term “Dasein” as the name of my blog, which is frequently used by Heidegger to denote humans. It looks to me as a term refering to a person who would like to think, to reflect on his life and try to look for a meaning of it and live a better life. For me, this is the most important reason why I would like to write blogs and I hope the readers are also this kind of people. By calling you Dasein, I shows my respect to you and express my pleasure in meeting you.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  
</search>
