<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<search>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>随想(0)</title>
    <link href="/2023/07/27/%E9%9A%8F%E6%83%B3(0)/"/>
    <url>/2023/07/27/%E9%9A%8F%E6%83%B3(0)/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>本文用于整理建站前曾发布在各社交平台的一些随想。</p><h1 id="知乎"><a href="#知乎" class="headerlink" title="知乎"></a>知乎</h1><ol><li><p>存在者存在，存在不存在<br>本性与表现之矛盾</p></li><li><p>人类逻辑的一致性何以可能？<br>是先天形成还是后天的规训？</p></li><li><p>We explain and predict phenomena.<br>We never truly understand them.</p><p>Initialy, our target is to find out the rules, after which, we boldly try to understand them, and this would cause tons of troubles and puzzles.</p></li><li><p>当我们直面事物本身，让它如它所是的那般显现，我们将无法把握这个事物的样子，除了“它是它”以外，我们无可言说。为了深入了解它，为了能够把握这个事物，我们提出了一系列范畴、性质、特点来规定事物，借着这些脚手架，摸索着事物的样子，用一系列问题拷打出它的真实。终于，我们用这些规定认识了事物的一系列特点，但我们脑中那个认识的事物已不再是其本身：这个事物本身绝不是这一系列特点的总和。我们用这些规定建构了对事物的抽象以对其进行认识（这一过程是必要且艰难的），但这一抽象也遮蔽了事物的真实面貌。</p></li></ol>]]></content>
    
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>随想</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>摘抄(0)</title>
    <link href="/2023/07/27/%E6%91%98%E6%8A%84(0)/"/>
    <url>/2023/07/27/%E6%91%98%E6%8A%84(0)/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>本文用于整理建站前曾发布在各社交平台的名言摘录与思考。</p><h1 id="知乎"><a href="#知乎" class="headerlink" title="知乎"></a>知乎</h1><ol><li><blockquote><p>在这种情況下，我们就不是以空论家的姿态，手中拿了一套现成的新原理向世界喝道：真理在这里，向它跪拜吧！我们是从世界本身的原理中为世界阐发新原理。我们并不向世界说：‘停止斗争吧，你的全部斗争都是无谓之举’，而是给它一个真正的斗争口号。我们只向世界指明它究竟为什么而斗争；而意识则是世界应该具备的东西，不管世界愿意与否。<br>《马克思恩格斯全集》，人民出版社1956年版，第1卷，第418页。</p></blockquote></li><li><blockquote><p>他们径直以人生行为准则，交托给人们的情感要求。<br>他们似乎彻底不承认有外在准则可循。所以孟子总要争辩义在内而不在外。在他看，勉循外面标准，只是义的袭取，只是‘行仁义’而非‘由仁义行’。<br>《中国文化要义》P97</p></blockquote></li><li><blockquote><p>逻辑不是关于思维的外在形式的学说，而是关于一切物质的、自然的和精神的事物的发展规律的学说。<br>冯友兰《中国哲学史新编》第四节，引列宁论述黑格尔《逻辑学》</p></blockquote></li><li><blockquote><p>人类自古以来，总是在自己圈内才有情理讲，在自己圈外就讲力（这是自古及今未曾变的真理）。<br>《中国文化要义》</p></blockquote></li><li><blockquote><p>“Sie sind ein gescheiter Junge, Einstein, ein ganz gescheiter Jung, Aber sie haben einen großen Fehler: sie Lassen sich nichts sagen!”<br>Weber:”You’re a clever fellow! But you have one fault. You won’t let anyone tell you a thing. You won’t let anyone tell you a thing”.<br><Einstein></p></blockquote></li><li><blockquote><p>Becoming is conscious, being unconscious.<br><My view of the world></p></blockquote></li></ol>]]></content>
    
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>摘抄</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>“寻找”还是“遇到”？</title>
    <link href="/2023/07/27/%E5%AF%BB%E6%89%BE%E8%BF%98%E6%98%AF%E9%81%87%E5%88%B0/"/>
    <url>/2023/07/27/%E5%AF%BB%E6%89%BE%E8%BF%98%E6%98%AF%E9%81%87%E5%88%B0/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>本文引用内容于2022.11.1发布于校内论坛，建立博客后进行搬运</em></p><p>写这些文字的起因是，有位同学在论坛上说：</p><blockquote><p>“爱情不能被找到的，爱情只能在转角遇到”</p></blockquote><p>当时的我恰在思考一些关于爱情的问题，便一时兴起放任了自己的表达欲，在论坛上大谈起自己的爱情观，寄希望于可以找到思考类似问题的人一起讨论想法，后来觉得这种行为有些不妥，但既然已经发了也便懒得删掉了。</p><blockquote><p>忽然想到一个问题，如果不去寻找，又要怎么遇到呢？</p><p>（声明：本人无任何感情经历，以下内容纯粹是主观臆断）感觉每个人心中都或多或少对自己的soul mate有一些朴素的期待或者说形象的幻想，可能这个期待并不真实合理，但它是存在的，它有点像一把尺子，我们用它去判断是否应该和某人开始一段关系。但是这把尺子上的很多内容并不是偶尔的一些接触就可以发现或确认的，这需要我们进一步的接触，至少需要成为普通朋友那种经常接触的关系才会得以展现。那如果想“遇到”爱情，就需要这种“前置工作”，即先成为朋友。但至少从你校特殊的情况来看，生活中异性的朋友是很少的，大部分人都只是停留在名字能对上脸但完全没说过话的阶段，那在这种情况下又如何“遇到”爱情呢？这似乎使得“遇到”本身也成为了一种寻找，寻找一些可能符合自己期待的人来成为朋友，进一步接触来了解对方。顺带一提，我对当下年轻人短期恋爱（短期内确认关系，然后可能没多久就分了）的理解就是把这种朋友关系提前视作恋爱关系，但这种观点下什么是恋爱关系似乎又说不清了，总之感觉应该是一种递进的关系，只是我们把称为“恋爱”的门槛降低了</p><p>好了，胡扯完了，有没有谈过恋爱的大佬来批判一下（</p></blockquote><p>或许是在公共平台上讨论爱情观的行为有些过于逆天了，后来一个展开讨论的回复也没有（笑）。但从当下看来，这些想法似乎还是有些问题。</p><p>可能是从小被灌输了比较强的性别观念的缘故，在中学阶段，除了自己有些朦胧的好感的女生，基本上社交圈子里就没有女生了，如果不是因为某些必要的外界压力强行推动交流的进行，平时也很少和女生说话，甚至说起来也有些躲躲闪闪的扭捏。当然，这种现象在大学并没有好转，我所在的大学的性别比例着实一言难尽，而物理系更是将这一特征表现到了极致（但最近的一些经历让我有了些改变，在此暂且按下不表）。这种在现在的我看来近乎病态的成长经历（可惜这种病态似乎在当下是十分普遍的），让我对和异性的交流有些奇怪的看法，以至于会觉得，尝试去接近一个异性都是出于“恋爱”的目的，而因此会对一些和异性的日常交流进行刻意的回避：只要能找男生解决的问题绝对不找女生。</p><p>性别这一特征在我的社交中被无限放大，以至于我完全忘却了在异性间还存在正常的朋友关系，而在这种正常的朋友关系中，“遇到”是可能的。两个人的接触与熟络不必总是以恋爱的动机为驱动，爱情的萌芽可以在日渐深入的接触中逐渐萌发。与此相对的是，以爱情为动机而开始的“友谊”，反倒可能因为过于拧巴而引来不良的后果。</p><p>但从当下实际看来，这一思路的可行性并不高，广泛出现的病态经历与观念背后，自有其深厚的现实基础。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>爱情</tag>
      
      <tag>人生</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Hello World</title>
    <link href="/2023/07/26/hello-world/"/>
    <url>/2023/07/26/hello-world/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to my blog! My name is Alexander Zhang and this is my very first post.</p><h1 id="What-happened-before-the-birth-of-this-website"><a href="#What-happened-before-the-birth-of-this-website" class="headerlink" title="What happened before the birth of this website"></a>What happened before the birth of this website</h1><p>For a long period of time, I recorded my thoughts on <a href="https://www.zhihu.com/people/professor-x-73/pins">Zhihu</a> and local word files on my computer. However, I found it hard to manage and review my records and I really hope to share some of the ideas to other people. So, eventually, I made up my mind to build up this blog to record my thoughts.</p><p>I have been considering building my own blog since 2022, but my lack of related knowledge prevented me from taking actions. Today, July 26th, 2023, I am happy to announce an official end of my sophomore year, which could also be considered as end of my bachelor life considering I have almost gathered all the course credits needed for graduation. A more reasonable date should be 9th July, but not until today have I finished all the short-term required missions (a TOEFL test is to blame for the delay). As a reward of finishing all these missions, I finally decide to sit down and build up my own blog by following a <a href="https://zhuanlan.zhihu.com/p/102592286">tutorial on Zhihu</a>. Anyway, here it is!</p><h1 id="What-is-this-blog-mainly-about"><a href="#What-is-this-blog-mainly-about" class="headerlink" title="What is this blog mainly about"></a>What is this blog mainly about</h1><p>Generally speaking, it’s about thoughts and knowledge.<br>Thoughts refer to philosophical thinkings and ideas gained from daily experiences.<br>Knowledge is mainly about physics, which is my major.</p><h1 id="How-this-blog-is-going-to-work"><a href="#How-this-blog-is-going-to-work" class="headerlink" title="How this blog is going to work"></a>How this blog is going to work</h1><p>I plan to use both Chinese and English to write blogs. Chinese for thoughts and English for knowledge. This result from the fact that, as a native Chinese speaker, it would be easier for me to express my emotions and thoughts precisely using Chinese. And I usually learn knowledge through English in the university.</p><h1 id="Why-“DASEIN”"><a href="#Why-“DASEIN”" class="headerlink" title="Why “DASEIN”"></a>Why “DASEIN”</h1><p>For a long time, I have been a great fan of Existentialism and I decided to use the term “Dasein” as the name of my blog, which is frequently used by Heidegger to denote humans. It looks to me as a term refering to a person who would like to think, to reflect on his life and try to look for a meaning of it and live a better life. For me, this is the most important reason why I would like to write blogs and I hope the readers are also this kind of people. By calling you Dasein, I shows my respect to you and express my pleasure in meeting you.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  
</search>
