<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<search>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>回家</title>
    <link href="/2023/07/29/%E5%9B%9E%E5%AE%B6/"/>
    <url>/2023/07/29/%E5%9B%9E%E5%AE%B6/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>中学时，每周最期待的事就是回家：周六的下午，夕阳的光辉撒在走廊里的行李箱上，下课后记下作业，从抽屉里摸出周末要用的习题册，码放在桌子上再收进包里，和同学互相吹捧着谁又提前写完了多少作业可以爽玩一个周末，在欢笑声与万向轮的隆隆声响中，走向校门，寻找拥堵的车流中熟悉的号码。那时的周末，虽有作业的烦恼，但到家之后最先做的事还是锁上房门开始玩手机：恶补追更的网络小说这周更新的章节、看看关注的up主又发了什么视频……完成了这些必要的打卡任务后，开始在贤者模式的“悔恨”之中，心不在焉地写写作业。</p><p>或许是用来放松的印象过于深刻，自高考结束后，几乎未曾能在房间里静下来学些东西。但本就可以随时刷手机的大学生活让我不再有回家的打卡任务，于是，在家的状态就变成了，无聊地打游戏水群消磨时间。而从高中开始，小区门口便一直在修路，让人毫无出门的动力。于是假期回家逐渐变成了一件无聊而痛苦的事，每天无所事事，又被自己什么都没干的内疚折磨着。回家的动力，除了第一年需要考驾照外，只剩下和旧友相约出游以及见见亲人，但前者不常有，后者呆久了也便逐渐麻木了。</p><p>这个暑假，不知是有意还是无意，我大幅减少了自己在家呆着的时间：考完试后是学院安排的一周科研实践；回来后便开始去老师课题组里参观、实践；组里放假后转战托福考试；考完试在北京瞎溜达几天……7.6便考完试的我，迟迟拖到今天才回到家里。回来之前考虑着要不要一周后便回北京继续做科研实践，亦或出去旅游转转，两周后还有一个为期一周的社会实践早就放上了日程，紧接着便是军训、开学。</p><p>“家”，这个我逐渐长大的地方，这间住了十多年的屋子，忽然变成了一个不可久留之所。与其称之为回家，不如说是回到这个自己熟悉的地方旅游休假几天。</p><p>我的根似乎还在这里，对这里的一切都那么熟悉，每次到来都有种安心的感觉，看到自己“今生今世的证据”。我熟悉这房中每一个物件的位置和样子，认得出楼下院子里的香椿、金银花、种下的葱和辣椒，还有那在我的作文中出现了不知多少次的被砍倒的竹林留下的瘦弱遗孤。我还认得小区里绿化的树木和无处不在的蝉鸣、时常凑在楼下聊天的奶奶们、每天变换着位置但总是出现在楼前的那几辆车……</p><p>但我又似乎已经远离了这里，许多事物逐渐陌生起来。邻居的雨棚又换了新色，门口的商铺和广场翻修易主了不知多少次现在里面又是卖着什么样的东西，家门口的菜园又添了许多杂草看起来荒芜了很多，甚至母亲的发型也从记忆中的长发改换为了短发……</p><p>这个地方，于我而言究竟意味着什么呢？</p>]]></content>
    
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>人生</tag>
      
      <tag>生活</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>为什么写博客</title>
    <link href="/2023/07/28/%E4%B8%BA%E4%BB%80%E4%B9%88%E5%86%99%E5%8D%9A%E5%AE%A2/"/>
    <url>/2023/07/28/%E4%B8%BA%E4%BB%80%E4%B9%88%E5%86%99%E5%8D%9A%E5%AE%A2/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>在公共社交平台高度发达的当下，自己建一个几乎没有人会看的博客似乎是一件不可理喻的事，需要被一堆技术问题困扰，也不及在社交平台上发布方便，这也正是我此前放弃建站的一个主要原因。</p><p>借着刚完成建站的兴奋劲，我尝试回顾究竟是什么坚定了我这次建站的决心。很快，我找到了一个不见得正确但很可以说服自己的答案：<strong>分享欲</strong>。</p><p>去年年底在放开前夕的隔离经历，对我的思想造成了极大的影响，其中一个方面便是让我认识到了自己对孤独的恐惧。我向来是一个喜欢独来独往的人，一个自以为能忍受孤独的人：中学的假期基本上都是宅在家打游戏，很少会和同学约出去玩；看电影、逛景点也都喜欢一个人去，可以沉浸在自己的想法中不被打扰……但那段经历让我意识到自己此前并不孤独，虽然是在独自一人做事，但往往可以有适合的人分享自己的收获和感受，而在隔离期间，自己仿佛和朋友们生活在了不同的世界，很多想法找不到人诉说，仿佛自己被从世界上抹去了，没有任何人注视着我，也没有人可以理解我。那是一种来自灵魂深处的孤独，一种对一个人的存在与价值的否定。</p><p>在孤独感的映衬下，我意识到了自己的表达欲与分享欲，开始明白为什么自己每天在社交平台上花几个小时水群聊天，也开始更加珍视这群可以一起聊天的人。从日常的学校生活到专业课知识的理解，都有合适的朋友可以分享（这从我到现在都没有发过关于物理的内容也可以看出，但客观来讲最大的阻碍是latex和markdown的转换问题），但是唯独对一些所谓的人生问题的思考，自己对哲学半吊子的爱好，却未曾找到合适的人交流。似乎这些问题太过普遍，和谁都可以谈，但又太过严肃和沉重，和谁聊天都无法将话题转到这上面：很难想象突然一本正经地和朋友说“我们来聊聊人生的意义吧”这种话。</p><p>开始时我只是享受思考和收获的过程，后来渐渐喜欢在常用的平台以及云盘的加密空间中，以私密的方式记录自己的思考。但这种记录方式时常会和我的日常生活交杂在一起，使其变得难以回顾；由于觉得不适合在社交平台公开发布这些内容而设置的私密权限，也挫败了对分享的渴望。而博客看起来是我目前接触到的最适合的记录和表达方式。</p><p>在各种社交平台十分火爆的当下，还在使用博客进行交流的人本来就少之又少，这不仅是对合适的读者群体的一种筛选，而且这群人在选择阅读博客时，本身对内容的期待也与社交平台上有所不同。更为严肃的内容或许可以更自然地直接被摆到台面上来讨论，在这样的读者群体中或许也更容易找到能够一起交流的人。但博客的这些特点也导致了其阅读量极少，自己的博客或许很难被人发现之类的问题。好在这对于未曾生活在聚光灯下的我来说不算什么大问题，此前的记录方式完全杜绝了分享的可能性，些许的在未来可能会有人读起这些文字的希望已经足够聊以自慰了。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>人生</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>随想(0)</title>
    <link href="/2023/07/27/%E9%9A%8F%E6%83%B3(0)/"/>
    <url>/2023/07/27/%E9%9A%8F%E6%83%B3(0)/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>本文用于整理建站前曾发布在各社交平台的一些随想。</p><h1 id="知乎"><a href="#知乎" class="headerlink" title="知乎"></a>知乎</h1><ol><li><p>存在者存在，存在不存在<br>本性与表现之矛盾</p></li><li><p>人类逻辑的一致性何以可能？<br>是先天形成还是后天的规训？</p></li><li><p>We explain and predict phenomena.<br>We never truly understand them.</p><p>Initialy, our target is to find out the rules, after which, we boldly try to understand them, and this would cause tons of troubles and puzzles.</p></li><li><p>当我们直面事物本身，让它如它所是的那般显现，我们将无法把握这个事物的样子，除了“它是它”以外，我们无可言说。为了深入了解它，为了能够把握这个事物，我们提出了一系列范畴、性质、特点来规定事物，借着这些脚手架，摸索着事物的样子，用一系列问题拷打出它的真实。终于，我们用这些规定认识了事物的一系列特点，但我们脑中那个认识的事物已不再是其本身：这个事物本身绝不是这一系列特点的总和。我们用这些规定建构了对事物的抽象以对其进行认识（这一过程是必要且艰难的），但这一抽象也遮蔽了事物的真实面貌。</p></li></ol><h1 id="QQ"><a href="#QQ" class="headerlink" title="QQ"></a>QQ</h1><p>这场在冬天开始，又在冬天“结束”的疫情，本身似乎也如一个冬天，想起了刘亮程的《寒风吹彻》：</p><blockquote><p>但在我周围，肯定有个别人不能像我一样度过冬天。他们被留住了。冬天总是一年一年地弄冷一个人，先是一条腿、一块骨头、一副表情、一种心情……尔后整个人生。</p></blockquote><p>重读《寒风吹彻》，久久不能释怀。<br>疫情中的各位，被冻到什么程度了呢？</p>]]></content>
    
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>随想</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>摘抄(0)</title>
    <link href="/2023/07/27/%E6%91%98%E6%8A%84(0)/"/>
    <url>/2023/07/27/%E6%91%98%E6%8A%84(0)/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>本文用于整理建站前曾发布在各社交平台的名言摘录与思考。</p><h1 id="知乎"><a href="#知乎" class="headerlink" title="知乎"></a>知乎</h1><ol><li>在这种情況下，我们就不是以空论家的姿态，手中拿了一套现成的新原理向世界喝道：真理在这里，向它跪拜吧！我们是从世界本身的原理中为世界阐发新原理。我们并不向世界说：‘停止斗争吧，你的全部斗争都是无谓之举’，而是给它一个真正的斗争口号。我们只向世界指明它究竟为什么而斗争；而意识则是世界应该具备的东西，不管世界愿意与否。<br>《马克思恩格斯全集》，人民出版社1956年版，第1卷，第418页。</li><li>他们径直以人生行为准则，交托给人们的情感要求。<br>他们似乎彻底不承认有外在准则可循。所以孟子总要争辩义在内而不在外。在他看，勉循外面标准，只是义的袭取，只是‘行仁义’而非‘由仁义行’。<br>《中国文化要义》P97</li><li>逻辑不是关于思维的外在形式的学说，而是关于一切物质的、自然的和精神的事物的发展规律的学说。<br>冯友兰《中国哲学史新编》第四节，引列宁论述黑格尔《逻辑学》</li><li>人类自古以来，总是在自己圈内才有情理讲，在自己圈外就讲力（这是自古及今未曾变的真理）。<br>《中国文化要义》</li><li>“Sie sind ein gescheiter Junge, Einstein, ein ganz gescheiter Jung, Aber sie haben einen großen Fehler: sie Lassen sich nichts sagen!”<br>Weber:”You’re a clever fellow! But you have one fault. You won’t let anyone tell you a thing. You won’t let anyone tell you a thing”.<br>《Einstein》</li><li>Becoming is conscious, being unconscious.<br>《My view of the world》</li></ol><h1 id="论坛"><a href="#论坛" class="headerlink" title="论坛"></a>论坛</h1><p>It wasn t what I saw that stopped me, Max, it was what I didn t see. Do you understand that? What I didn t see. In all that sprawling city, there was everything except an end. There was no end. What I did not see was where the whole thing came to an end, the end of the world. Take a piano, hmm? The keys begin, the keys end. You know there are 88 of them. Nobody can tell you different. <strong>They are not infinite. You are infinite. And on those keys, the music that you can make is infinite.</strong> I like that. That I can live by.You get me up on that gangway and you rill out in front of me a keyboard of millions of keys, Millions and billions of keys that never end. That s the truth, Max, they never end. That keyboard is infinite. <strong>And if that keyboard is infinite, then on that keyboard there is no music you can play. You are sitting on the wrong bench. That s God s piano.</strong> Christ! Did you see the streets? Just the street—–there were thousands of them. How do you do it down there? <strong>How do you choose just one? One woman, one house, one piece of land to call your own, one landscape to look at, one way to die.</strong> All that world just weighing down on you. You don t even know where it comes to an end.<br>……<br><strong>Land?Land is a ship too big for me. It s a woman too beautiful, it s avoyage too long, a perfume too strong, it s music I don t know how tomake.</strong><br>《The legend of 1900》</p><h1 id="QQ"><a href="#QQ" class="headerlink" title="QQ"></a>QQ</h1><ol><li>Everybody believes in the exponential law of errors [i.e., the Normal distribution]: the experimenters, because they think it can be proved by mathematics; and the mathematicians, because they believe it has been established by observation.</li><li>See, there’s three kinds of people: dicks, pussies and assholes. Pussies think everyone can get along, and dicks just want to fuck all the time without thinking it through. But then you got your assholes. And all the assholes want us to shit all over everything! So, pussies may get mad at dicks once in a while, because pussies get fucked by dicks. But dicks also fuck assholes. And if they didn’t fuck the assholes, you know what you’d get? You’d get your dick and your pussy all covered in shit!</li><li>I went to the woods because I wished to live deliberately, to front only the essential facts of life, and see if I could not learn what it had to teach, and not, when I came to die, discover that I had not lived.I did not wish to live what was not life, living is so dear; nor did I wish to practice resignation, unless it was quite necessary. I wanted to live deep and suck out all the marrow of life, to live so sturdily and Spartan-like as to put to rout all that was not life, to cut a broad swath and shave close, to drive life into a corner, and reduce it to its lowest terms, and, if it proved to be mean, why then to get the whole and genuine meanness of it, and publish its meanness to the world; or if it were sublime, to know it by experience, and be able to give a true account of it in my next excursion.</li><li>All knowledge is, in the final analysis, history.<br>All sciences are, in the abstract, mathematics.<br>All methods of acquiring knowledge are, essentially, through statistics.</li><li>With 4 parameters I can fit an elephant, and with 5 I can make him wiggle his trunk.</li><li>Scientists are too contentious and too morally and intellectually fragile to follow any method consistently.</li><li>Thermodynamics is a funny subject.The first time you go through it,you don’t understand it at all.The second time you go through it,you think you understand it,except for one or two points.The third time you go through it,you know you don’t understand it,but by that time you are so used to the subject,it doesn’t bother you anymore.</li></ol>]]></content>
    
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>摘抄</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>“寻找”还是“遇到”？</title>
    <link href="/2023/07/27/%E5%AF%BB%E6%89%BE%E8%BF%98%E6%98%AF%E9%81%87%E5%88%B0/"/>
    <url>/2023/07/27/%E5%AF%BB%E6%89%BE%E8%BF%98%E6%98%AF%E9%81%87%E5%88%B0/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>本文引用内容于2022.11.1发布于校内论坛，建立博客后进行搬运</em></p><p>写这些文字的起因是，有位同学在论坛上说：</p><blockquote><p>“爱情不能被找到的，爱情只能在转角遇到”</p></blockquote><p>当时的我恰在思考一些关于爱情的问题，便一时兴起放任了自己的表达欲，在论坛上大谈起自己的爱情观，寄希望于可以找到思考类似问题的人一起讨论想法，后来觉得这种行为有些不妥，但既然已经发了也便懒得删掉了。</p><blockquote><p>忽然想到一个问题，如果不去寻找，又要怎么遇到呢？</p><p>（声明：本人无任何感情经历，以下内容纯粹是主观臆断）感觉每个人心中都或多或少对自己的soul mate有一些朴素的期待或者说形象的幻想，可能这个期待并不真实合理，但它是存在的，它有点像一把尺子，我们用它去判断是否应该和某人开始一段关系。但是这把尺子上的很多内容并不是偶尔的一些接触就可以发现或确认的，这需要我们进一步的接触，至少需要成为普通朋友那种经常接触的关系才会得以展现。那如果想“遇到”爱情，就需要这种“前置工作”，即先成为朋友。但至少从你校特殊的情况来看，生活中异性的朋友是很少的，大部分人都只是停留在名字能对上脸但完全没说过话的阶段，那在这种情况下又如何“遇到”爱情呢？这似乎使得“遇到”本身也成为了一种寻找，寻找一些可能符合自己期待的人来成为朋友，进一步接触来了解对方。顺带一提，我对当下年轻人短期恋爱（短期内确认关系，然后可能没多久就分了）的理解就是把这种朋友关系提前视作恋爱关系，但这种观点下什么是恋爱关系似乎又说不清了，总之感觉应该是一种递进的关系，只是我们把称为“恋爱”的门槛降低了</p><p>好了，胡扯完了，有没有谈过恋爱的大佬来批判一下（</p></blockquote><p>或许是在公共平台上讨论爱情观的行为有些过于逆天了，后来一个展开讨论的回复也没有（笑）。但从当下看来，这些想法似乎还是有些问题。</p><p>可能是从小被灌输了比较强的性别观念的缘故，在中学阶段，除了自己有些朦胧的好感的女生，基本上社交圈子里就没有女生了，如果不是因为某些必要的外界压力强行推动交流的进行，平时也很少和女生说话，甚至说起来也有些躲躲闪闪的扭捏。当然，这种现象在大学并没有好转，我所在的大学的性别比例着实一言难尽，而物理系更是将这一特征表现到了极致（但最近的一些经历让我有了些改变，在此暂且按下不表）。这种在现在的我看来近乎病态的成长经历（可惜这种病态似乎在当下是十分普遍的），让我对和异性的交流有些奇怪的看法，以至于会觉得，尝试去接近一个异性都是出于“恋爱”的目的，而因此会对一些和异性的日常交流进行刻意的回避：只要能找男生解决的问题绝对不找女生。</p><p>性别这一特征在我的社交中被无限放大，以至于我完全忘却了在异性间还存在正常的朋友关系，而在这种正常的朋友关系中，“遇到”是可能的。两个人的接触与熟络不必总是以恋爱的动机为驱动，爱情的萌芽可以在日渐深入的接触中逐渐萌发。与此相对的是，以爱情为动机而开始的“友谊”，反倒可能因为过于拧巴而引来不良的后果。</p><p>但从当下实际看来，这一思路的可行性并不高，广泛出现的病态经历与观念背后，自有其深厚的现实基础。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>人生</tag>
      
      <tag>爱情</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Hello World</title>
    <link href="/2023/07/26/hello-world/"/>
    <url>/2023/07/26/hello-world/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to my blog! My name is Alexander Zhang and this is my very first post.</p><h1 id="What-happened-before-the-birth-of-this-website"><a href="#What-happened-before-the-birth-of-this-website" class="headerlink" title="What happened before the birth of this website"></a>What happened before the birth of this website</h1><p>For a long period of time, I recorded my thoughts on <a href="https://www.zhihu.com/people/professor-x-73/pins">Zhihu</a> and local word files on my computer. However, I found it hard to manage and review my records and I really hope to share some of the ideas to other people. So, eventually, I made up my mind to build up this blog to record my thoughts.</p><p>I have been considering building my own blog since 2022, but my lack of related knowledge prevented me from taking actions. Today, July 26th, 2023, I am happy to announce an official end of my sophomore year, which could also be considered as end of my bachelor life considering I have almost gathered all the course credits needed for graduation. A more reasonable date should be 9th July, but not until today have I finished all the short-term required missions (a TOEFL test is to blame for the delay). As a reward of finishing all these missions, I finally decide to sit down and build up my own blog by following a <a href="https://zhuanlan.zhihu.com/p/102592286">tutorial on Zhihu</a>. Anyway, here it is!</p><h1 id="What-is-this-blog-mainly-about"><a href="#What-is-this-blog-mainly-about" class="headerlink" title="What is this blog mainly about"></a>What is this blog mainly about</h1><p>Generally speaking, it’s about thoughts and knowledge.<br>Thoughts refer to philosophical thinkings and ideas gained from daily experiences.<br>Knowledge is mainly about physics, which is my major.</p><h1 id="How-this-blog-is-going-to-work"><a href="#How-this-blog-is-going-to-work" class="headerlink" title="How this blog is going to work"></a>How this blog is going to work</h1><p>I plan to use both Chinese and English to write blogs. Chinese for thoughts and English for knowledge. This result from the fact that, as a native Chinese speaker, it would be easier for me to express my emotions and thoughts precisely using Chinese. And I usually learn knowledge through English in the university.</p><h1 id="Why-“DASEIN”"><a href="#Why-“DASEIN”" class="headerlink" title="Why “DASEIN”"></a>Why “DASEIN”</h1><p>For a long time, I have been a great fan of Existentialism and I decided to use the term “Dasein” as the name of my blog, which is frequently used by Heidegger to denote humans. It looks to me as a term refering to a person who would like to think, to reflect on his life and try to look for a meaning of it and live a better life. For me, this is the most important reason why I would like to write blogs and I hope the readers are also this kind of people. By calling you Dasein, I shows my respect to you and express my pleasure in meeting you.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  
</search>
